hello welcome to the BNB connection this
is episode seven with me is Brad
shonfeld and uh this episode is going to
be on evidence-based
Fitness so Bradley uh you wrote a very
good uh blog post a very good guest blog
post for me a couple years
back uh called the hierarchy of
knowledge do you have that in front of
you any
chance I do okay so I thought we could
start off this podcast by having you go
through that a little bit so uh first of
all who this blog post that you wrote
was based on a book written by poy yeah
it's portney and Watkins uh basically
there it's one of the seminal texts uh
that we have in in research and
evidence-based practice and uh uh the I
would recommend everyone gets it and
this is an adaptation of their their
work so they have is it five steps or is
it a is it five it's a hierarchy of five
uh five different levels of knowledge so
before we before we get into the
hierarchy itself is this hierarchy mean
that uh that there are different so this
Hier hierarchy is going to go through
the different forms of
exercise but does it mean that one form
is better than the other or is it give
you like a an evaluation of which are
the best
methods correct yeah well and better is
is somewhat subjective but that there
are different levels of of knowledge and
that uh if you're looking for more
scientifically based knowledge the
higher up you go generally the more
appropriate that's going to be for
drawing conclusions and we we'll talk a
little more as to why in terms of the
objectivity of the evidence the control
when we're talking about the scientific
method but really what we're talking
about the the first level the bottom
level if you will would be tradition and
tradition says that I'm GNA do something
because other people have done it in the
past uh good uh one of my favorite uh
topics here is the donut if you've ever
watched a baseball game where they use
the dut with the weighted donut to swing
a bat uh people have done that forever
well there's been a lot of research
showing that if you swing a weighted bat
right before you go up to hit it
actually decreases your ability to
produce Forest yet people continue to do
it why just because it was done in the
past I've spoken with Eric cressie and
another friend of yours as well really
astute Fitness Pro another baseball
analogy uh baseball pitchers Every
Spring training you seeing them running
lap after lap they'll run several miles
why does a pitcher ever have to run he
stays on the mound he'll throw a pitch
wait 20 seconds till another pitch how
does this apply to the specificity apply
to it doesn't why does they do it
tradition so really tradition is the
oldest form uh or or the lowest form of
knowledge and um generally we want to
stay away from that now there could be
benefits there could be uses for it but
certainly you would hope that certain
things have passed the test of time just
because something is done before you
doesn't necessarily mean that it's a
good way to go about it so tradition is
the lowest rung this is the lowest form
of evidence out of the five that you're
going to go through today that's correct
does this mean you should ignore
tradition well no as I mentioned it's
it's not you you don't want to ignore
anything because there could be a basis
for it the fact that as I said it has
stood the test of time there's certain
things that could mean that it might
have some value and if you don't have
other supporting evidence some of the
other hierarchy when you're going up the
ladder you would look to the highest
level first that would be your last form
of deferral if you will the tradition
angle uh but generally speaking that
would not be a good form it would be the
you could not be or I would not be very
confident in making decisions just
because something had tradition behind
it um your next level is Authority and
I'm sure we all know how people tend to
uh defer to Authority just because
someone has a higher degree or they're a
well-known strength coach Fitness Pro uh
we will tend to trust their opinions and
a good uh give you a good example here
uh I just published a uh paper with Alan
Aragon and James creger was a m analysis
on nutrient timing well I was a big
proponent of nutrient timing and I to
some degree felt pray to the
authority aspect I read the classic text
by Ivan Portman John iy some other uh
very popular and renowned um nutritional
professionals speak about it and I been
aware of some of the research as well
but the fact that some of these
authority figures had uh discussed it so
much uh as as a viable strategy that led
me to believe that hey I can trust this
and after doing a lot of my own research
found it not to be true and as a matter
of fact uh Dr John Ivy had posted a uh
or had written a review in a paper
challenging one of the papers that I had
written with evidence that really did
not support is or where that was very
skewed towards it towards the actual
topic and I actually tackled that in a
blog post and it really shows you that
just because someone is an authority
doesn't mean they're not prone towards
towards significant bias on a top so
that violates the tradition and the
authority
um forms of evidence
correct
violates you relied on this information
because that's a testament to the to the
authority yeah you you relied on like
nutrient ement we've been doing it for a
while because of tradition also the last
10 years uh maybe maybe not 10 years but
the last eight years it's just gone
without saying you need your protein
shake after your workout or you're gonna
you're wasting yeah but I would say
that's because of the authority that's
because people had just trust we were
trusting most people were just trusting
the authority it was in position papers
uh by certain organizations and and of
course these position papers were
written by Authority so it became
tradition through Authority but
tradition usually means it's done over a
somewhat longer period this is the topic
of nutrient timing really was probably a
dozen or so years uh where we're really
where that I remember reading about it
in like Arnold Schwarzenegger's uh
encyclopedia where he said
rest you know after your workout take
around 20 30 minutes for your blood to
get back to normal and then immediately
slam a eat a big meal of protein or slam
a protein drink or something like that
because uh everything goes back to
Arnold then well you know and it makes
sense it's it's logical you know you
just did a hard workout you need that
you need the proteins you know but that
this goes to show you why it's important
to go move up along the chain of
hierarchy so what's next the next is
trial and error where basically you try
something see how it works and then
adjust based upon whether it's working
well or not now the problem there is is
that that is generally an N equals one
and it's not in a controlled uh you
don't do it in a controlled fashion
there's no control based on it so it's
privy towards bias towards what you're
seeing which might not necessarily be
indicative of uh of an actual effect the
proper effect and look n equals one is a
very effective technique for a given
person so we know that research just
shows Norms just shows
memes of different groups and that
people respond differently and we'll get
more into this there's High responders
low responders and basically you get
means between that people who respond
differently there's a lot of
interindividual differences so we need
to then take what we have and then apply
it to an individual and then use trial
eror but if you're using trial and error
without basing it on some scientific
process the scientific Methodist we'll
talk about uh discuss your starting
point you have no idea where you're
starting so your trial and error can be
wildly uh ineffective in terms of how
you're you're grasping at it and by the
way just because something proves to be
effective in what you're doing doesn't
mean something else might be more
effective this is one thing I hear all
the time is that well look at the great
results I'm getting
well that's fine that doesn't mean you
might not have gotten better results
doing something
else um the next one the uh second
highest to the top would be logical
reasoning and this is a big uh component
of the top wrong scientific method but
logical reasoning we look for to logic
we it's a systematic
process where you combine personal
experience your intellect and various
formal uh thought systems to come about
with a an opinion on the
topic um you can use deductive reasoning
which is um where theory is used to
create a hypothesis uh or you can use
inductive reasoning where you use
generalizations that are drawn from
various observations now these are are
valid uh techniques they are they go and
Lear with the scientific method but just
because something is logical as we know
doesn't NE necessarily mean that it adds
up we could say it's logical that doing
crunches should make your midsection
flatter it should reduce the you think
that right you're doing exercise you're
getting I mean or you could think that
but as we know through research that
logic does not always translate into
practice and we see this all the time
there's so many logical assumptions we
make as as scientists that when we apply
the scientific method and subject them
to research that don't pan out and that
finally leads us to the last one which
is the scientific method uh that is a
systematic controlled critical way of
examining a subject so we're going to
look to control if you're doing a true
experiment you look to control as many
variables as possible other than the one
that you will manipulate and uh
systematically then take two groups that
are very similar to one another and draw
conclusions from
that and if you
it objectively then there should be very
little to no bias uh in the uh
conclusions that you
draw but there are plenty of limitations
as as you well know uh so ultimately
what we're going to look at is uh when
we talk about this evidence-based
process is taking what we know through
research through the scientific method
looking at the body of research and then
combining that with our own personal
experience as well as the needs and this
is very important which a lot of people
Miss it's not just taking the research
and saying okay this is what the
research shows so this is what we're
going to do we look to our experience
from that and then look at the needs and
abilities of the individual and with all
that we're then going to draw
conclusions as to how to properly go
about working with that specific
individual So speaking of research are
there um types of research articles that
are is there a hierarchy in in research
absolutely uh we generally you want to
look to your what are called your
randomized controlled trials where
you're uh systematically as I mentioned
before manipulating one variable where
you control the other variables and and
then um you can draw causality from that
uh the observational studies uh such as
a lot of the epidemiological work that's
done uh they look to correlations they
look at associations between various um
topics and we know that correlation does
not
necessarily uh lead to causation we know
that ice cream eating ice cream is
correlated to murders uh that doesn't
mean that eating ice cream causes
murders that means that usually you're
reading ice cream in the hot summer days
and that there's a correlation more
towards the fact that it's uh the hot
summer days can cause uh leads to other
crimes so again we have to be careful
when drawing uh causality but that again
doesn't mean that again a lot of people
I know will dismiss observational
research and that's misguided because we
we can draw a lot of of great many of
the greatest um conclusions that have
been drawn in terms of of our what we do
today has been drawn through
epidemiologic
research um what about case studies is
that a high form of
research again case studies are it's
when you say say high it's certainly not
on the level of experimental research so
that you're going to have different
gradations that would depend upon case
study can be effective but that is an N
equals one now a series of case studies
can end up being quite effective because
you're then drawing your you're being
able to pull certain things so what's
the benefit and the drawback of case
studies well the specific drawback is
that it's an N equals one so just
because one person responded you you
don't get statistical power and you're
not uh there's no comparative source
that you're looking you're not
controlling one variable I I mean just
uh looking at one variable with while
controlling everything else when you're
doing a case study basically a case
study you're looking at one person and
you don't there's no comparative source
so that really goes back to an N equals
one you could have an outlier for
example correct or not only an outlier
but that person uh there there can be
all sorts of reasons that you're getting
one effect in terms of things they're
doing uh that's not controlled that you
wouldn't know unless you had other but
the benefit is that you can often with a
case study delve really deep into one
you know particular area get some in a
broad set of information with that one
person that you wouldn't be able to do
with a so it's good to know the
strengths and drawbacks let's talk about
review papers the strengths and
weaknesses and also meta analyses so
what are the strengths and weaknesses of
a review paper well the certainly the
the weakness of a review paper is that
there's often a lot of uh subjectivity
in it and bias uh as someone like myself
and you as well who've written a lot of
research papers uh you know that um
someone can be quite biased now the
peerreview
process hopefully should take out some
of that but the re the reviewers
themselves are going to be subject to
bias and look they you're going to get
reviewers even in in randomized control
trials that have their own biases and
will try to steer things but um there is
no control to a review and you can in a
review you can selectively ignore a lot
of research if you either if you're
biased towards a particular you want to
show something Andor if you just don't
you're not a good or not I shouldn't say
good researcher but if you're not as
knowledgeable on the topic or don't
really understand certain things you can
not know certain research that you're
not including you miss it um and then
again if the reviewers that really would
be up to the reviewers if they don't
catch that uh so there's a lot of
subjectivity now the the benefit to it
is especially when it's done well is
that you get a good
overall um view of a topic as well as
the fact that it allows you to it gives
you a hopefully a broad-based idea of
the literature so the first thing
generally I'm going to do if I'm looking
at a topic that I'm not aware of is got
to review papers and then look at their
list of references to draw upon and then
try to select out the references that I
think would be very important there if
not looking at all of them looking at a
good collection from uh depending on the
journals that are they're published in
the authors on their profiles and other
factors so certainly that can be a um a
good way a good way to uh at least get a
an overview on a topic before studying
it more in depth uh the ma analysis that
you brought up uh is a a really cool
topic and what that does it
pulls the results of hopefully all the
studies and by the way I should just
take a step back and mention so that was
a narrative review which I mentioned
before there is something called a
systematic review which is a step up
from the uh narrative review where
there's a systematized process that you
use and it tends to take out some of the
subjectivity uh within a uh a review but
the M analysis really is considered the
highest form of evidence-based practice
if you look at the evidence-based
practice guidelines they gravitate
towards meta analysis because it's a
systematized way of taking all the
studies on a topic within a certain
inclusion exclusion criteria so you'll
look a good researcher that's doing a ma
analysis will um will try to hone in on
what they're looking for and exclude
certain studies that aren't relevant
because if you include all studies and
and there are some let's say well you're
looking like I did did protein timing
did this protein timing MAA analysis if
you would look at all studies well
supposing a study gave someone two grams
of protein we we use the criteria of
roughly 18 grams of protein six grams of
essential amino acids suppos on to study
that two grams of protein and it was a
low quality it was gelatin where they
again you would you'd have to qualify uh
that because that might not be showing
the true effect so you we're supposing
someone did a study it was two weeks in
length hypertrophy study where you're
not going to get those the results that
you want right so most in most uh
situations in strength and conditioning
here's the problem ideally any topic we
were curious about we could just pop on
hop onto PubMed and find a Open Access
meta analyses of every single topic or a
systemized review or a narrative review
but there are so many topics in strength
and conditioning it and it's it's so you
know you don't it's not a field that's
has you know a ton of research so you
rarely rarely find that in fact a lot of
topics don't have any research on it and
so let's talk uh we've
got 10 minutes remaining let's talk
about how an evidencebased person would
go about trying to educate themselves on
a topic let's let's talk about a couple
different
scenarios let's say I'm a powerlifter
and I'm like I want to or no I'm just a
lifter and I want to learn about
powerlifting do I just start looking at
research papers on powerlifting and then
start trying to formulate how I
train by reading what the journal
articles have to say about
powerlifting no again absolutely not but
what you want to do as as we discussed
earlier
based
practice but research has many gaps in
it when you're doing a research study uh
you both you and I know that uh it's
each study is just one piece to a puzzle
and that there were huge uh gaps in in
much of the literature that we just
can't properly assess because especially
with something like EX ex endless number
of ways you can carry out uh exercise
carry out program design uh and trying
to study them is a NeverEnding process
and and you're you're really left with
um with a lot lot of gaps in this so
what I I think in the evidence-based way
is to make yourself aware of what the
literature shows but then you do look
you have to then appreciate this is a
key element here you have to understand
the limitations to what these studies
are showing so you understand these gaps
and then you look to personal experience
as well as your own body so you'll take
this research you take your own
experience and you can there's nothing
wrong so the we talked about the
hierarch the hierarchy um yeah can you
consult with other uh authorities on it
that that's a good way you know the if
you know the research that's the first
key because if someone just tells you
hey drink three bottles of castor oil
and your uh your on RMS are going to go
up by 20%
he's an expert he's got a PhD in
biomechanics well that doesn't mean
anything you would know through the
literature that that's not that's a
ridiculous uh comment I mean the point
I'm trying to make Brad is that it would
be silly for any person to try to learn
powerlifting through the research alone
right but you but if you are trying to
be the best powerlifter possible you
would want to know some stuff about the
research so here's how I would go about
it if I'm just a regular lifter and I
want to learn about powerlifting I'm
going to look at what different routines
are out there how the different
powerlifters train how do raw
powerlifters train how do geared
powerlifters train how do steroid users
train how do natural lifters train what
are some of the most popular methods out
there I'm going to look at message
boards and see what topics are discussed
I'm going to try to join a gym and ask
them and you know talk to the lifters
and say what should I do how do I you
know how what type of routine should I
learn starting out how's my form what
assistance exercise do you do what sets
and Reps should I do what periodization
form should I use what program should I
be on what are the popular programs I'll
look into them and you and try to become
friends with lifters who know a lot as
well but as you gain experience you know
you will learn that powerlifters tend to
follow tradition they tend to tell you
what to do what what works for them you
know you should do this program well
that's coincidentally the same program
that they're on will that work best for
your body how do you know how to tailor
things towards your body well you need
to learn a little bit more about
biomechanics you need to and then you
incorporate that information into your
training and you see if it works you
could put it through trial and error and
it's this constant to
me the the evidence-based Fitness or
evidence-based coaching or
evidence-based lifting it's not about
just relying on published research it's
this constant um art and skill of
utilizing and ranking and filtering all
the forms of evidence whether it's
anecdotes or published research or logic
or whatever and you know qualifying them
and saying okay this I can trust this
I'm a little bit skeptical about and
then employ you know trying it and and
then basically like the Bruce Lee quote
absorbing what's useful disregarding
what's useless you know so
um let's talk about uh you want to be an
evidence-based strength coach and you're
just an everyday lifter can you become a
good strength coach just by reading the
research well again and and I completely
agree with what you said so training and
I thought I had made this clear but
maybe you kind of got lost that training
is a science and an art uh when you're
talking about some of the stuff that you
are a lot of that is Art but you can't
and the art is great the art is
necessary but you can't be an artist in
this context in the science Pace field
without understanding the underlying
science so can you can you be a
bodybuilder can you be a powerlifter
just going around a gym sure will you
necessarily reach your potential
probably not because you're then just
relying on these lower higher uh the
lower uh
hierarchal uh aspects so again to me you
you need to have an appreciation so yeah
I look I'm a bodybuilder I have been for
years I learned through trial and error
through going to the gym just like you
said but it wasn't I wasn't able to take
my physique to the next level and to
take clients of mine when I was training
them to the next level until I really
had an appreciation for the science the
more scientific aspects there are still
bodybuilders who are doing concentration
curls because they think that it's
getting the peak in their biceps uh or
or doing um crunches because they think
it's is reducing their their midsection
so again we do have to have an
appreciation for the science so yeah do
and even to to go off of your what you
talked about earlier your paper with
nutrient timing yeah you can be a good
bodybuilder but some of the things you
might be doing are unnecessarily painful
if you're a slave to your nutrient
timing and you think that you need to
eat every 90 minutes or you're going go
you're going to go
catabolic and you're you stay up on the
evidence and you read res search and you
come across this paper that you and
Allan and James wrote you'll say okay
it's not as important as I thought I
don't have to be a slave I can eat you
know it works best for my schedule to
eat four four meals a day instead of six
and since I ate a big meal before I
worked out I don't need to worry about
eating right right after my workout or
something like that but it may it gives
you that's to me that's the essence of
being
evidence-based um by using all these
different forms of evidence and you know
as I'm a lifter at heart I'm a a gym rat
you know I love talking to my stronger
friends about their own
training and you know I always like to
hear what they're doing what's worked
for them that's what all good lifters do
but you just know that it's an anecdote
you it Sparks your curiosity you might
say I'm going to try that or you might
not but you listen to anecdotes but then
at the end of the day to me what uh the
culmination of being evidence based is
saying you know is to be in a position
where you can publish research or
conduct your own experiment about it and
be SCI utilize the scientific method and
say you know what I am so curious about
this I'm going to control all these
variables and just look at this one
question and really hone in on it and
try and answer it myself because you
know being a a scientific minded lifter
I'm so curious about all these types of
things and I'm sure every lifter out
there is so curious about different
things
but unless you can use a scientific
method and unless you have enough you
know sample size you'll never know
you'll never really know the answer to
it you'll have to just rely on Lower
forms of evidence yeah yeah and I mean
as a bodybuilder certainly I uh I'm
going to look at people like John
Meadows I mean he's he's inventing all
these new routines and stuff we haven't
studied those does that mean that well I
can't do that because it's not in the
research that would be ridiculous to to
think that so we need as a matter of
fact most good research comes in in an
applied science like exercise from the
field so we need uh people that are in
the field that are looking at these
Innovative techniques to then try to
study them and often the so many
limitations to the to the tools that
we're using the sensitivity of them uh
that again I think your point is really
well taken that we need to be aware of
what people are doing we need to follow
that as well as the research Brad we've
got about minute or two left
yeah minute and a half why don't we end
on the uh TRX story that you've told
me oh yeah so uh that's one of my
favorites a good friend of mine Jay dos
was um at uh some Fitness conference and
they they were watching the people doing
TRX and one of the this prominent
researcher who's evidently a real
research nerd turned to Jay and says uh
is that validated and Jay turned to him
and said uh
gravity so uh you know this is the type
of thinking that that's a lot of
researchers have they're not one of the
things I think that separates yourself
and I from some of the researchers is
that we're also practitioners and have
been for for many years so that it gives
us perspective and that uh you can't
just look at things in that context I
call them research snobs I can look at
an exercise and go oh that that's you
know that's probably going to work well
and then I'll try it and make my
decision I won't I don't need uh you
know a randomiz I don't need a
randomized controlled trial to tell me
that this exercises might be good I you
know I'll I I I know enough about
biomechanics to see for myself but the
point is not to be a you know research
snob is to just know the forms of
evidence the ranking and the hierarchy
of them and try to make decisions to the
best of your abilities based on all the
evidence around you knowing that you
know ideally you'd have hell ideally
we'd have a metaanalysis with everything
but say you want to know you know what's
the best exercise for transferring to
the vertical jump or
what's what's the safest um you know I
want to my I have low back problems but
I want to do an exercise that loads up
my quads but easy on my low back how
would you go about answering that you
know um there's lots of tools of
available to you there's research on
this there's if you figure out how to
calculate or estimate spinal loading you
know there's there's then if you just
know good strength coaches a lot of them
will tell you try the Bulgarian split
squat try the you know try doing single
leg exercise try a reverse lunge or
something you know um so there's lots of
evidence out there lots of tools lots of
forms of evidence use them all but just
kind of know uh you know be aware of the
the um the hierarchy be aware of well
this is this expert's opinion and
experts are often
wrong experts are biased we all are we
can't help it it's a human it's an
inherent human
trait so um anyway this is a a good
podcast Brad thank you for shedding
light on the hierarchy anything else to
add yeah one last point is that uh we
and this kind of goes to what you just
said is that we must if we want to
actually optimize our programs we must
remain objective we could probably do
another podcast on this but all too
often PE uh Fitness Pros get hardened
into a certain way of thinking and they
don't want to then consider that they
might be wrong and and as scientists
there's no crime in being wrong it's not
even wrong you believe certain certain
things based upon the evidence that you
have at one point and if something
happens in the future that shows
otherwise we need to be um willing and
and embrace the fact that uh science uh
guides our processes so never be afraid
to change based upon new
evidence yep my favorite one of my
favorite quotes is from my my supervisor
John Cronin and he he always
says this is what I know today and this
is subject to change Tomorrow based on
new evidence that comes out so you just
flow with the research you know amen
okay
Bradley signing out